I was scouring the internet in a
shark-like frenzy to find my next topic
to discuss when I stumbled across an
interview the famous fitness and
nutrition influencer Mr. Thomas Dauour
hosted with a peptide clinician Dr. Joy
Kong who is triple boardcertified in
addiction psychiatry and anti-aging. In
that interview there was a discussion of
a peptide that I'd never run across
before but seemed to have Mr. Dauour and
Dr. Kong really quite excited,
especially for its metabolism effects
and anti-fat gain effects like those one
might expect from something like a GLP-1
receptor agonist that we've seen become
extremely popular of late. So, we'll see
if there's any scientific merit based on
a big study that Thomas mentions and
then we'll discuss how to increase this
peptide in ourselves. The peptide is
named Mott C. When it comes down to like
fat loss in general, I think let's give
kind of a soup to nuts breakdown of what
happens with the mitochondria and fat
oxidation to begin with because I think
you know we can hear people say okay
yeah it's going to help the mitochondria
but how is the mitochondria actually
what is beta oxidation what's happening
there well it's a utilization of uh so
is is the the biochemical process of how
fat is digested and metabolized um I I
don't know the exact biochemical
pathways. But uh but definitely if you
increase the efficiency of that process,
then you can grab more fat cells and
actually use your fuel much more
efficiently rather than somebody who who
can't really produce energy from that
process easily. Then fat will sit there
and then you're still sluggish. So if
you can enhance this process, all of a
sudden you have weight loss and enhanced
energy level. So, we need to have
efficient fat metabolism to be able to
lead to greater fat loss. What does that
mean? Well, as a quick correction to Dr.
Kong, fat cells aren't grabbed
themselves. In fact, it's the fat
molecules within the fat cells that are
released into the bloodstream and then
delivered to various energy demanding
cells. Once inside these cells to their
point, fat molecules are taken up inside
mitochondria and undergo a biochemical
pathway called beta oxidation. I won't
bog this down with too much more
complexity, but since your fat molecules
are these chains of carbon atoms, so
beta oxidation is the process where uh
pairs of carbon atoms are lobbed off of
the chain and eventually get converted
to usable energy by the mitochondria.
There's a lot of complexity there, but
we have a lot of much more interesting
things to get to. So, we'll leave it
there. But just know that uh for you to
lose body fat, your fat cells must
release or themselves convert fat
molecules into usable cellular energy
called ATP. One of the things that I've
seen with Matsi that's particularly
interesting and you know we don't have
to get too far in the weeds of this is
is
uh how it actually works, how it
actually is created. So for I read a
study earlier this week that was quite
interesting. It was I think it was
nature communication study. They had
human arm and they had a rodent arm with
it. I don't know if you've seen this
paper, but on the rodent arm of it, it
was really fascinating. They saw like
these massive changes in like tumor
necrosis factor alpha interlucan 6 like
massive reductions. There was even I
think it was like a 21% reduction in
obesity when they were feeding them a
highfat diet to try to induce obesity.
So there's like a massive just like sort
of blockage of lip um basically
lipogenesis to begin with. Okay, let's
start there. First, Mr. Dauer correctly
mentioned that there was a rodent arm
where much of the research was
performed, although there was also a
human part that we'll get to. First, did
these animals experience a blockage in
fat gain, obesity in those that are
exposed to this MC peptide? Yep, he's
right. As shown here, in fact, he
downplayed it or just misremembered some
of the the numbers. The effect was
closer to 50% or more. We see the
relative fat mass on the vertical axis
and we see the time on the horizontal
axis. The black dots are the control
mice, those not exposed to MOS CI and
the two red conditions are the ones
exposed to Mati on a highfat diet.
That's the HFD up top. So, a huge
protective effect against fat gain.
Specifically, the data I just showed you
is in CD1 mice, which are outbred mice,
meaning that they're genetically
distinct like most humans are. They
repeated these experiments in the more
traditional genetically similar C-57
black 6J mice and showed similar
results. Okay, pretty impressive. But
how does it do that? Well, remember when
we discussed beta oxidation and how it's
a critical biochemical process for fat
molecule utilization for energy? The
researchers measured in muscle cells
through a measure called oxygen
consumption rate. I've actually had the
pleasure of doing these experiments
myself as well as working with these
cells which I'll tell you a bit more in
a second. Oxygen consumption is related
to a mitochondria's ability to oxidize
or utilize substrate for energy
generation. In this case, too high
concentration of fat molecules
palmitate. In this situation, the cells
were either treated with MOS CI or not.
And we can see the control condition did
not experience an increase in oxygen
consumption, but the MOS peptide exposed
cells did. This would suggest that the
cells take up fat molecules and oxidize
or utilize them to a much greater degree
that the overall fat gain is
significantly reduced even when
consuming a high energy diet. Instead of
being stored in fat cells, the fat
molecules are eliminated through beta
oxidation and mitochondrial metabolism.
Super cool. Two quick cautions here
before we move on. One, these are
myoblasts. So the cells were immature
muscle cells. results that might differ
in more mature cells. I doubt it, but it
is a possibility. Second, this is one
measure, so we'd likely need more to be
sure of this being a main mechanism at
play here. Okay, I'm going to get into
some more details on how Matsi works,
including some more discoveries related
to the peptide in the extended version
of this video that you're watching. If
uh you're a get to the point kind of
person, it's probably not for you. But
if you want to learn uh a lot more about
this peptide, join the Physionic
Insiders research review. You get access
to exclusive library of videos like the
one that you're watching right now. But
you also get weekly research reviews, uh
private podcast access, and we'll get to
engage in live sessions where we discuss
uh the science even more. There's more
perks, but uh you get the idea. The link
is in the description if you're
interested. Now, before we go onto the
human data and how to increase this
peptide in our body, let me discuss one
more metabolic effect. We've been over
how it leads to reduce fat gain. And we
saw one way that it could do that,
enhanced fat molecule utilization.
However, there's another metric that
extends beyond just looking at isolated
immature muscle cells called an RER or
respiratory exchange ratio. If RER is
lower, it means that the body on average
is using more fat for energy. If we look
at that data, we have the RER on the
left side. Remember, lower is more fat
utilization and metabolism. Now, there
are four conditions here. They're
separated not only by MOS C peptide
exposure, but also by age during a big
chunk of the day indicated by the P
value well below 0.05 there. All
conditions except the old non-matsy
exposed animals have reduced reer.
Interestingly, younger mice exposed to
Matsi do not experience a reduced re. So
the effect is age dependent. All of
these data indicate that Matsy peptide
has a metabolism effect, but the effect
might be more pronounced in older
subjects, in this case animals. Anyway,
let's discuss the human data, but let's
have Thomas Dauer explain the findings
first. And the human arm was they had
subjects do like 4 hours of exercise.
There were relatively sedentary people
that did four hours of exercise. And
there was afterwards a 12-fold increase
in MOT C. And that was one of the first
like major indicators of like okay this
is secreted or created or produced when
we exercise just like GLP1 is produced
when we eat fiber when we eat protein
etc. Yeah. So he's absolutely right. Uh
we can see the experimental design in
humans here. They measured peak V2. So,
a measure of cardiorespiratory function.
And then 48 hours later had people train
for 10 cycles of one minute at peak or
near peak V2 with a 75 seconds of active
recovery between cycles. During and
after, the researchers took muscle
biopsies and blood samples. Blood
samples only during the exercise. Here
are the results. You can ignore the left
side unless you're a molecular
biologist. You'll understand that
section. The two graphs are for muscle
on the left and blood on the right.
Exactly to Thomas's point, MC C peptide
levels, the actual protein was around 12
times elevated. In fact, while the
results indicate the effect is
transient, it does seem that during and
immediately post exercise there's an
elevation. Technically after 4 hours
there's no longer an elevation but that
might also be because the standard error
bar there is massive indicating a lot of
spread in the data. So yes we can
produce this protein in our body through
exercise. So could this be another of
many many mechanisms by which exercise
improves our health? Although admittedly
we don't generally see much fat loss
from exercise alone. That could be
explained by the transient nature of
this peptide. Maybe if we get to a point
where it's always present, we might see
some profound effects. Something to keep
an eye on. The takeaway here is one,
yes, MOS C looks like a promising
peptide based on these pre-clinical
data. Two, it does not function the same
way that GLP1 receptor agnus do and I
don't think that we have enough data yet
to say it's better. Uh, we're in early
days. However, three Matzi is produced
during exercise, but the effect is
transient. That all said, there's only
one final thing to
say. Have you seen this video? No. This
is one of my favorite videos. Okay, to
be honest, I don't know this video well,
but it might be worth it anyway. I'll
see you over there. And bring the M Sea
with you.
[Music]